A Finding Aid to the Nickolas Muray Papers, 1910-1978, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Nickolas Muray papers
1910-1992
Archives of American Art
Muray, Nickolas, 1892-1965
AAA.muranick
Archival Resource Key
1.5 Linear feet
The papers of photographer Nickolas Muray measure 1.5 linear feet and date from 1910 to 1978. Found within the papers are biographical materials; business and personal correspondence, including a handful of letters from Frida Kahlo; writings; teaching files, primarily of photography courses taught at New York University; printed material; artwork; and photographic materials of Muray, his family and friends, and his work. There is a 0.6 linear feet Unprocessed Addition which includes biographical material, correspondence, photographs, research notes and a diary about Africa, and a subject file on the book The Revealing Eye, Personalities of the 1920s, written by Paul Gallico with photographs taken by Muray, 1967.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated in 1988 and 2019 by Muray's daughter, Mimi Murray.
Existence and Location of Copies
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2016 and is available on the Archives of American Art's website. Materials which have not been scanned include blank pages, blank versos of photographs, and duplicates. In some cases, published books and other publications have had their covers, title pages, and relevant pages scanned.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical / Historical
Photographer Nickolas Muray (1892-1965) lived and worked in New York, New York and was known for his portrait, fashion, and advertising photography and for his mastery of the carbro color printing process.
Born in Szeged, Hungary, Muray spent time in Budapest as an engraver's apprentice and moved to Germany at the age of 16 to expand his technical knowledge of photo-engraving and photography. In 1913, Muray immigrated to America where he worked as a photo engraver at Stockinger Engraving Co. and eventually opened his own photography studio in 1920. After successfully completing a commission to photograph Broadway star Florence Reed, Muray continued to build his portfolio with regular commissions for Harper's Bazaar and Vanity Fair to photograph movie stars, artists, musicians, artists, and models. In the 1930s, Muray mastered the carbro printing process and established one of the first color labs in America. His color fashion and advertising work continued to appear regularly in Vogue, Ladies' Home Journal, Woman's Home Companion, McCall's and other periodicals.
In addition to his professional work, Muray wrote reviews for Dance magazine and represented the United States in 1928 and 1932 as a member of the Olympic fencing team. He maintained a long distance affair with artist Frida Kahlo throughout the 1930s, eventually ending the relationship but remaining friends until her death in 1954. In 1942, Muray married his fourth wife, Margaret (Peggy) Schwab, with whom he had a daughter, Mimi. Muray died of a heart attack in 1965.
Scope and Contents
The papers of photographer Nickolas Muray measure 1.5 linear feet and date from 1910 to 1992. Found within the papers are biographical materials; business and personal correspondence, including a handful of letters from Frida Kahlo; writings; teaching files, primarily of photography courses taught at New York University; printed material; artwork; and photographic materials of Muray, his family and friends, and his work.
There is a 0.6 linear feet Unprocessed Addition which includes biographical material, correspondence, photographs, research notes and a diary about Africa, and a subject file on the book The Revealing Eye, Personalities of the 1920s, written by Paul Gallico with photographs taken by Muray, 1967.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 2 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Nickolas Muray papers, 1910-1978 (0.9 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, OV 3)
Series 2: Unprocessed Addition, 1927-1992 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 4-5)
Other Finding Aids
Finding aid available at Archives of American Art offices.
Photography -- Study and teaching; Photographers -- United States; Portrait photography; Photographs; Latino and Latin American artists; Kahlo, Frida; New York University -- Faculty
- Nickolas Muray Papers, 1910-1978; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 3
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include curriculum vitae, identification cards related to Muray's particaption in Olympic fencing events, and membership related to the Circle of Confusion and the New York Coffee House Club. There is also a transcript of Muray's interview with the NY radio station WEAF regarding beauty and aesthetics, and documentation of Muray's 1961 heart attack and recovery.
  Correspondence is primarily with Muray's friends, business associates, and clients, including Martha Graham, Claude Monet, Ruth St. Denis, and H.G. Wells. There are also letters related to his participation in the Olympic Games, his application to the Army Signal Corps Photographic Services, and a handful of letters from Frida Kahlo that discouss her health, impending divorce from Diego Rivera, and plans regarding the exhibition of her artwork.
  Writings include an autobiographical account by Muray; lists and notes regarding celebrity portrait photo sittings; typescripts of theater perfermance reviews; and a mock-up of Great Tribes of the World, with photographs by Muray. There is also a typescript commentary of Revealing Eye by Paul Gallico.
  Teaching files are primarily course materials relating to Muray's 1940 and 1941 New York University photography classes and a lecture series based on his travels in Africa. Printed material includes a copy of Muray's book Celebrity Portraits of the Twenties and Thirties, a brochure advertising Muray Studios, clippings, and miscellaneous printed material.
  There are also a handful of sketches by illustrator Willy Pogany and photographic materials of Muray, his family and friends, and his work. Photographs include Muray in uniform as a member of the 1928 Olympic fencing team; carbro prints of Loretta Young, 3 models, and and arrangements of food; and a photograph of Muray with Miguel Covarrubias, Diego Rivera, and Frida Kahlo.
  - Biographical Material, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1950-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Identification Cards, Olympics, 1931-1932, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Interview Transcript, WEAF-NYC Radio, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Medical History, Heart Attack, 1961-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Memberships, circa 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - A-B, 1926-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes letters from Evangeline Adams, Judith Anderson, and the secretary to the King of Belgium.
    - C, 1925-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes letters to Hall Caine, Feodor Chaliapin, Miguel Covarrubias, and Joan Crawford, as well as a Christmas card from Frank Crowninshield decorated with an etching by Gari Melchers.
    - D-G, 1926-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes letters from John Galsworthy and Martha Graham.
    - H-K, 1926-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes letters from Jascha Heifetz, Joseph Hergesheimer, Hedda Hopper, and A.S. Hutchinson.
    - Kahlo, Frida, 1931-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - L-O, circa 1928-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes letters from Mary Martin, Claude Monet, and Agnes O'Neill. There are also two photographic Christmas cards of Murray in costume.
    - Olympic Games, 1954-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - P, circa 1925-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes a letter from Bessie Breuer Poor.
    - Parrott, Katherine Ursula, circa 1925-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes a profile of Muray by Parrott.
    - Q-S, 1925-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes letters from Ruth St. Denis, George Bernard Shaw's secretary, H. De Vere Stacpoole, and Frank Swinnerton.
    - Signal Corps Photographic Center, 1942-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - T-Z, circa 1926-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Includes letters from Carl Van Vechten, A.B. Walkley, and H.G. Wells.
  - Writings, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Autobiographical Account, circa 1950-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Book Mock-Up, Great Tribes of the World (unpublished), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lists, Celebrity Portraits, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Notes, Celebrity Photo Sittings, circa 1920-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Typescripts, Performance Reviews, circa 1920-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Typescript, On Revealing Eye by Paul Gallico, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Teaching Files, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Lecture Materials, Peoples of the World, 1957-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - NYU Photography Course, 1940-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - NYU Photography Course Notes, 1940-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Printed Material, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Book, Celebrity Portraits of the Twenties and Thirties by Nickolas Muray, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Brochure, Muray Studios, circa 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Clippings, 1920-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Clippings, 1943-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Artwork, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Sketches, circa 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographic Materials, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Nickolas Muray, Family, and Friends, circa 1910-1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Oversized materials housed in OV 3.
    - Nickolas Muray, Family, and Friends, circa 1931-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Studio of Nickolas Muray, circa 1920-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Advertising Work, Carbro Prints, circa 1950-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Oversized Photograph scanned with Box 2, Folder 10, circa 1928; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 3)
- Unprocessed Addition, 1927-1992; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 4-5
  The Unprocessed Addition includes biographical material, correspondence, photographs, research notes and a diary about Africa, and a subject file on the book The Revealing Eye, Personalities of the 1920s, written by Paul Gallico with photographs taken by Muray, 1967.
  - Unprocessed Addition, 1927-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
  - Unprocessed Addition, 1927-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 5)